<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-billpg-pop3-sleeping-00" ipr="none" submissionType="IETF" consensus="true"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">


    <front>
        <title abbrev="POP3-SLEEPING">POP3 - SLEEPING Extension</title>
        <author fullname="William Godfrey" initials="W." surname="Godfrey">
            <organization>billpg industries</organization>
            <address>
                <uri>https://billpg.com/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date month="October" year="2022" />
        <area>General</area>
        <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
        <keyword>pop3</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                An extension to POP3 allowing opened connections to be 
                shelved, avoiding the cost of repeated TCP and TLS handshakes 
                when polling for new messages and for message deletes to be 
                committed without having to disconnect.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">

            <t>
                When polling for new messages in a <xref target="RFC1939">POP3</xref> 
                mailbox, both client and server need to repeatedly re-negotitate TCP and
                TLS and re-authenticate every time the client attempts to poll for new messages.
                By allowing a client to keep an underying connection open instead of closing
                it down, the client is at liberty to resume using the opened connection at 
                a later time and so avoid the burden of all the steps needed to reconnect.
            </t>

            <t>
                This document specifies an extension that enables this mode of operation.
                It introduces a new SLEEP state, alongside the established
                states, with commands to enter and leave this new state. During the SLEEP state, 
                the client remains authenticated and the underlying connection remains open, but 
                the associated mailbox is unlocked and inaccessable.
            </t>

            <t>
                The underlying connection that remains open includes the TLS channel if present, 
                including if that channel was opened by an explicit <xref target="RFC2595">STLS command</xref>
                or implied by <xref target="RFC8314">use of TCP port 995</xref>.
            </t>
                
            <t>
                 Furthermore, the command to 
                leave the TRANSACTION state and enter SLEEP will also commit any pending message deletes
                made with the DELE command that would otherwise only be committed at the QUIT command.
            </t>

            <t>
                POP3 is designed to work on a simple bulk-download-and-delete model, 
                eschewing more advanced features such as folder management. This 
                extension is compatible with that model as the high-level operation of
                client and server is unchanged, only adding the ability to shelve an
                opened connection between polls.
            </t>

            <section title="Requirements Language">
                <t>
                    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
                    document are to be interpreted as described in 
                    <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

    <section anchor="capability" title="Capability">
      <t>A service implementing this extension indicates support by including
      the capability "SLEEPING" in response to a CAPA command.</t>

      <section anchor="iana_capa_sleeping" title="SLEEPING Capability">
        <t>
          <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">

            <t hangText="CAPA tag:"><vspace blankLines="0" />SLEEPING</t>
            <t hangText="Arguments:"><vspace blankLines="0" />none</t>
            <t hangText="Added commands:"><vspace blankLines="0" />SLEE, WAKE</t>
            <t hangText="Announced states / possible differences:"><vspace blankLines="0" />both / no</t>
            <t hangText="Commands valid in states:"><vspace blankLines="0" />SLEE in TRANSACTION, WAKE in SLEEP</t>
            <t hangText="Specification reference:"><vspace blankLines="0" />This document</t>
            <t hangText="Discussion:"><vspace blankLines="0" />
              The presence of the "SLEEPING" capability indicates the SLEEP state is supported and that the 
              SLEE and WAKE commands are supported to enter and leave this new state.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sleepstate" title="The SLEEP State">
      <t>
      This RFC introduces the SLEEP state, alongside the established states of AUTHORIZATION, TRANSACTION and UPDATE.
      </t>

      <t>During a SLEEP state, the underlying TCP and TLS connections remain open and active. Access tp the mailbox 
      is not possible but the client onetheless remains athenticated during this time.</t>

      <t>A client requests an opened connection enters the SLEEP state from the TRANSACTION state by a SLEE command. 
      If the server responds with a success +OK respose, the connection MUST exit the TRANSACTION state and enter
      the SLEEP state. If the server responds with a failure -ERR response, the opened connection MUST remain in the
      TRANSACTION stete.</t>

      <t>A client requests an opened connection returns to the TRANSACTION state by a WAKE command. If the server responds
      with a success +OK response, the collection MUST exit the SLEEP state and return to the TRANSACION state. If the 
      server responds with a failure -ERR response, the opened connection MUST remain in the SLEEP state.</t>
      
      <t>During the SLEEP state, the server MUST support these commands: NOOP, QUIT, WAKE.</t>

      <t>
        <list hangIndent="10" style="empty">
          <t>
            NOTE: This document STRONGLY encourages that during a sleep state, service implementations return error
            responses to any command other that the three listed above. This will assist those developing clients 
            from wrongly assuming commands such STAT or UIDL could be used during a SLEEP state to poll for new messages.
          </t>

          <t>
            NOTE: This document STRONGLY encourages those services that place a lock on a mailbox during a TRANSACTION state
            to release those locks during a SLEEP state and allow other concurrent requests.
            It is permitted for the WAKE command to fail with a "-ERR [INUSE]" failure response if a separate connection has taken the
            lock for the mailbox during the SLEEP state.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

      <section anchor="other_capabilities" title="Considerations for other capabilities">
        <t>"CAPA" <xref target="RFC2449" /> is not on the list of commands that are valid to use during the SLEEP state.</t>

        <t>
        Registered capabilities include a statement to which states each capability may be announced in, often using "both" as a
        shorthand for "both the AUTHOIZATION and TRANSACTION states". As this document does not introduce a new state when the
        CAPA command may be used, this document does not change the meaning of the capabilities registered.
        </t>
      </section>

    <section anchor="slecommand" title="The SLEE Command">

      <t>The client sends a SLEE command to complete a TRANSACTION state session. Any messages that were flagged for deletion by
       DELE (and not reverted by RSET) MUST be deleted by the server if it responds with a +OK success response.</t>

      <t>The client MUST wait for a response to this command before sending any new comands, regardless of the 
      <xref target="RFC2449">PIPELINING</xref> capability.</t>

      <t>A service that responds with a success +OK response to a SLEE command MUST have completed both these steps. 
      If the service cannot perform these steps, it MUST return an error -ERR response and leave the state of the mailbox unchnaged.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="wakecommand" title="The WAKE Command">
    </section>

    <section anchor="noopcommand" title="The NOOP Command">
    </section>

    <section anchor="quitcommand" title="The QUIT Command">
    </section>


  </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1939.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2595.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8314.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2449.xml"/>
        </references>
    </back>

</rfc>


